Spencer Family Papers, 1738-1876
Connecticut Historical Society
Spencer Family Papers
1738-1876
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Spencer family
1.25 linear feet (2.5 boxes)
Biographical Sketch
Elam Chaffee was born in Somers, Connecticut March 11, 1783, and died there January 5, 1855. He married Elizabeth (1787-1865), daughter of Ezekiel and Elizabeth (Chapin) Spencer in 1808. Elam worked at the U.S. Armory in Springfield. Mass., finishing bayonets. In 1817 he and his brother-in-law, Chester Spencer, were partners in Somers as traders and storekeepers under the name of Spencer and Chaffee. Elam and Elizabeth’s children were born in Springfield, but the family moved to Somers sometime after 1821.
Chester Spencer, in addition to his mercantile ventures was also involved in textile production—he was partner in the construction of a woolen mill in Somers and in 1835 purchased two satinette looms. He married Rebecca Hamilton and had children Mandana, Theodore (b. ca. 1815), Salvina and Asa.
Scope and Content
The collection primarily consists of financial and legal documents of a Somers, Connecticut family who were merchants and farmer. The papers were arranged chronologically by person, starting with the elder Ebenezer Spencer who is represented by land and probate records, 1738-1740. His son, Ebenezer, is represented by deeds and by his will, 1754-1800. The papers of Ezekiel Spencer, son of the second Ebenezer, consists of legal and estate records, 1815-1820 while the papers of his son Ezekiel Jr. concern some debt he found himself in, 1816, 1820.
The bulk of the collection is related to Chester Spencer who served as constable in Somers and as a result his papers include justice court records, writs and summonses, 1818-1848. Of note are liquor licenses he held from 1824-1834, and among his bills of sale and deeds, textile-related documents. Records of the partnership of Spencer and Chaffee date from 1816-1840 and consist of financial and legal records.
Chester’s son Theodore is also represented by assorted documents including financial records and a license, 1863. Additional Spencer family papers are also arranged chronologically although in most cases the exact relationship is unknown.
Somers town records consist of subscriptions, one to aid a fire victim, the other to start a school; land surveys; a lease for a grist mill; minutes of a school meeting; and a notice to electors of an upcoming meeting, 1793-1837. Court records include summonses, depositions and writs, 1800-1858.
A rather large number of unidentified or papers that could not be attributed to any single family member are arranged in the final box. These include bills related to building a fulling mill and purchasing looms. Also of interest are recipes for mixtures used for medicinal purposes and business cards from Hartford and Springfield.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Spencer, Chester, b. 1783.; Spencer, Ebenezer, d. 1740; Spencer, Ebenezer, d. after 1779.; Spencer, Ezekiel, 1748-1820.; Spencer, Ezekiel, b. 1779.; Spencer, Theodore.
Family Names
Spencer family.
Subjects
Billheads --Connecticut --Hartford.; Decedents’ estates --Connecticut --Somers.; Deeds --Connecticut --Somers.; Textile industry --Connecticut --Somers.; Somers (Conn.) --History --Sources.
Contents:
- Papers
  - Ebenezer Spencer land and probate records, 1738-1740 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ebenezer Spencer deeds and will, 1754-1784 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ebenezer Spencer deeds, 1792, 1800 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ezekiel Spencer legal and estate records, 1815-1820 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ezekiel Spencer Jr. legal documents regarding debt, 1816, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chester Spencer correspondence, 1826-1848 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chester Spencer writs and summonses, 1818-1848 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Chester Spencer deeds and bills of sale, 1822-1851 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chester Spencer constable’s records, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chester Spencer liquor licenses, 1824-1834 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chester Spencer bonds, 1820-1835 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chester Spencer assorted legal papers, 1823-1847 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chester Spencer promissory notes, 1816-1843 (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
  - Chester Spencer bills and receipts, 1818-1869 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Chester Spencer bills and receipts, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Spencer and Chafee financial and legal papers, 1816-1840 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Theodore Spencer letter and license, bills, 1863, 1852, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Theodore Spencer bills, notes and receipts, 1863-1870, undated (Box 2, Folder 4-8)
  - Asa H. Spencer financial and estate records, 1827-1833 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Samuel Spencer financial and estate records, 1827-1837 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - S. Spencer & Co. bills and receipts, 1837-1839 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mrs. D. Spencer bills and receipts, 1870-1873 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Spencer family papers, 1824-1869 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Somers town records, 1793-1837 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Court records: summonses, depositions, writs, etc., 1800-1858 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Assorted bills, receipts, etc. not associated with the Spencer family, 1817-1876, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Bills related to building a fulling mill and purchasing looms, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Financial memoranda books, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Recipes for medicinal uses, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Business cards from Hartford and Springfield, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)